A Guide to the Papers of Alexander H. H. Stuart and the related Stuart and Baldwin families
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Alexander H. H. Stuart and the related Stuart and Baldwin families 1754-1921
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
228-a
ca. 800 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift 1994 March 3
Biographical/Historical Information
For biographical information concerning Archibald Stuart and Alexander H.H. Stuart, please consult Dictionary of American Biography, Volume XVIII, pages 160-162.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of the additional papers of the Stuart and Baldwin families, chiefly Archibald Stuart (1757-1832) and Alexander H.H. Stuart (1807-1891), of Staunton, Virginia, ca. 1754-1921, ca. 800 items (4 Hollinger boxes, 1.5 linear feet), including correspondence; financial and legal papers; printed items; microfilm; an architectural drawing; Civil War military papers of Captain George M. Cochran, Jr.; nineteenth century newsclippings; drafts of speeches by Alexander H.H. Stuart; land grants signed by Virginia governors, including Beverley Randolph, Robert Brooke, John Floyd, and James Monroe; two engravings of Alexander H.H. Stuart; and papers regarding the settlement of the estate of Archibald Stuart. Since Alexander H.H. Stuart was a prominent member of the Virginia Whig Party, there is considerable material in this collection concerning the Whig Party and Virginia politics.
CORRESPONDENCE OF THE STUART-BALDWIN FAMILY -SUMMARIES (BOX 1)
Martha S. Baldwin forwards a letter to her husband General Briscoe Gerard Baldwin (d. 1852) from their daughter Mary Baldwin regarding her health (n.d.)
James Barbour (1775-1842), Secretary of War, mentions an interview with [Henry] Clay concerning the participation of members of the administration in the political convention [of the National Republican Party ] and discusses his knowledge of the true charges leveled against Andrew Jackson while in control of Louisiana during the War of 1812, Jackson's conflict with Louisiana Governor William Charles Claiborne and the Governor of Georgia, his refusal to obey the orders of President Monroe, his denunciation of Madison, and his behavior as acting Governor of Florida (1827 Dec 16); Barbour also mentions his involvement in "a controversy of mixed vexation," his retirement, " and says, " [John C.] Calhoun 's pamphlet is the final act in the drama -and I apprehend the breach will become wider and wider" (1831 Feb 19)
G.A. Baxter, member of the Board of Visitors of Washington Academy, informs Archibald Stuart of his election to the Board, and explains why his resignation was errantly reported in their minutes (1807 Sep 29)
Robert Beverley discusses a possible land sale (1791 May 5); asks Archibald Stuart to attend to his properties near Staunton and make sure all back taxes are paid (1791 Nov 24); discusses land business and court matters (1791-1797); makes reference to the slave revolt in the French colony of Haiti in the West Indies and the declaration of independence by Toussaint L'Ouverture (1743-1803), criticizing George Washington for his early acknowledgement of the French Republic, believing he acted unconstitutionally, and expresses great confidence in the talents, integrity, and firmness of Mr. [John] Adams (1798 Dec 17)
John Breckinridge writes business letters (1788 & 1790), his son, J.C. Breckinridge, asks for information from Archibald Stuart for a biographical essay about his father (1815 Apr 30)
Gerald Briscoe, [Jr.?] writes about a land dispute in "Caintucke" (all three letters, 1794-1796, n.d.)
Cuthbert Bullitt to Archibald Stuart and General John Brown discusses a suit involving Colonel Clendenning for lack of payment on a bond (1790 Jan 2); and the death of his brother, Thomas Bullitt, asking for a petition in the Legislature of Virginia for their financial relief (1823 Dec 16)
Joseph C. Cabell refers to a pamphlet containing Mr. Madison's letter and an appendix establishing the point that the Tariff Policy is the true Republican doctrine; Cabell paid T.W. White, Richmond printer, for 3,000 copies and will have more printed if necessary; claims that the opposition party is exerting every effort to destroy Madison's influence in the state (1829 Feb 24)
Arthur Campbell requests an investigation into the circumstances surrounding the sickness and death of the boy Charles H. Campbell; speaks of the opposition to the federal constitution and the value of the controversy over the amendments to point out the real motives of those trying to keep Virginia and North Carolina from approving the Constitution (1789 Sep 2); discusses difficulties in obtaining land warrants due to the boundary dispute with Kentucky and refers to the petition to revise the Virginia State Constitution opposed by the friends of [Patrick ?] Henry (1795 Sep 30); refers to Thomas Jefferson and the success of the "friends of monarchy" who won the late election for President, and the French Revolution (1797 Feb 20); and mentions his desire that the land law in the Act of 1795 would be repealed or amended (1798 Dec 22)
John Coalter discusses a debt against Mrs. Reid, and declares "I have no hopes of the republic since New Jersey has proved recreant" (1812 Nov 6)
George Davis discusses legal and business matters (1792 Aug 17)
R. Gamble discusses legal and business matters (1791-1800)
Hugh Holmes writes concerning the competition between Winchester and Staunton to be the branch of the Virginia Bank which he believes must be kept exclusively under a Republican direction; asks for Archibald Stuart to secure a loan for five hundred dollars; discusses the rumor that merchants believe that the Eastern and Northern Tories have devised a stratagem to defeat the loan requested by the government to conduct the War of 1812 with Great Britain (1814 Mar 9); speaks of his pain from numerous operations; the raids of the Tunisian corsairs upon British ships in the English Channel (1817 Jul 12); and the death of Mary, the daughter of Archibald's brother Alexander (1823 May 6)
[Chapman ?] Johnson (1779-1849) sends a copy of a decree from the court of appeals in the case of [Doneghe ?] and Campbell to Archibald Stuart; sent a copy of Archibald Stuart 's letter about the seat of government to the Editor of The Enquirer for publication; refers to the failure of their efforts to establish the University of Virginia and his belief that nothing will be done for it this winter; the non-effect of political essays upon the public mind, and mention of "the great James River project" (1822 Mar 2)
John Lewis to Dabney Carr notes "my seeing Mr. Jefferson" is very uncertain, and writes about the Mayo v Lewis lawsuit (1768 Jan 23)
John Lewis to Thomas Jefferson writes regarding his lawsuit Mayo v Lewis, docketed in Thomas Jefferson 's hand (1772 Oct 4)
J. Marshall speaks of the fickleness of political parties in reference to "Zach." and refers to a business matter (n.d.)
George Mathews (1739-1812) writes of his safe arrival in Georgia where he was asked to sit for election to political office (1791 Oct 10); and details concerning his dispute over a land sale in Virginia and his motive in accepting the office of [Governor of Georgia?] (1794 Apr 4)
James D. McCutchen to Joseph Janney writes concerning his inability to make his payment for land due to the drought, high feed costs and poor crops and his proposal to work out an alternative method of payment (1839 Mar 25)
Andrew Moore (1752-1821), elected to the first four Congresses, March 4, 1789-March 3, 1797, writes from New York and Philadelphia, sends copies of all laws passed, wages established at six dollars per day, set the budget for the staff of the President and Vice-President, discusses office seekers, mentions that the amendments to the constitution are being conducted with a great deal of warmth, believes the amendments "will quiet the public mind and remove in a great measure the opposition to government" (1789 Aug 12); asks for help in securing compensation for a slave who escaped into Pennsylvania and proved that he was a free black unjustly sold to Moore who was unaware of his status by a previous owner (1791 Nov 5); the preoccupation of Congress with a bill fixing the rates of representation in Congress and the disputed election between General Anthony Wayne (1745-1796) and General James Jackson (1757-1806) before Congress (1792 Mar 15); his disappointment in the bill fixing the ratio of representation and the decision made in the House concerning the contested election which declared the seat vacant (1792 Mar 26); discusses the resignation of Thomas Jefferson as Secretary of State who appeared determined never to enter public life again, with the former Attorney General Edmund Randolph succeeding Jefferson as Secretary of State; mentions the great loss suffered by the country by Jefferson's resignation at this critical time and praises Jefferson highly; encloses a number of resolutions introduced by Mr. Madison, the conflict over the payment of interest on the debt of the United States; cites Jefferson's opinion on the same subject; forwards copies of the correspondence between Thomas Jefferson and Citizen Edmond Charles Genet and Jefferson's report on United States trade with Europe (1793 Jan 4); the attempt by Washington and Congress to have Citizen Genet recalled to France due to his insolent and insulting conduct (1793 Dec 8); the situation of the United States becoming more and more critical due to the increase of British spoliation on American shipping, detaining our vessels, and alleging that an old law precluded the United States from Britain's West Indian ports; the purchase of flour and beef and the chartering of United States vessels to transport it because the United States was bound by treaty to guarantee the French West Indies; Madison's resolutions; the empowerment of the President to impose an embargo on all shipping coming into American ports; the arming of small vessels to use against the Algerians; a bill providing for the defence of our ports and harbors; the establishment of arsenals, and a resolution for the enlistment of 15,000 troops, with training during 24 days a year, and the need for a direct tax to fund national defence (1794 Mar 14)
Garrett Peterson asks [Charles Anderson] Wickliffe for help in locating Archibald Stuart and buying a piece of land belonging to Archibald Stuart to make his title to his plantation more secure (1826 Jan 24, see Wickliffe's letter, 1826 Feb 26)
William Preston to William Anderson seeking advice in a land claim controversy (1783 Jan 1)
[Andrew Reid, Jr.] to Thomas J. Stuart writes a social letter to a friend (1807 Sep 5)
Alexander Farish Robertson Correspondence, chiefly with Philip Alexander Bruce concerning his history of the University of Virginia and especially the Honor System (1921)
John Steele writes that the Governor [Henry Lee] has written Mr. White asking him to help Archibald Stuart investigate the High Sheriff for embezzlement (1792 Mar 5)
Robert Sterritt notifies Joseph Janney that he has secured a purchaser for Archibald Stuart 's plantation in Rockbridge County, James D. McCutchen, (1837 Jul 14, see also McCutchen 1839 Mar 25)
Eleanor Briscoe Stuart to Thomas J. Stuart concerning his studies and vacation while at Washington Academy (1806 Jan 24 & Mar 2) and to her mother, Mrs. Margaret Briscoe (1808 Feb 19)
Martha M. Stuart writes to her mother-in-law, Mrs. Eleanor (Briscoe) Stuart concerning family news (n.y. Apr 8)
[Charles Anderson] Wickliffe (1788-1869) forwards a letter from Garrett Peterson to Archibald Stuart concerning a land sale (1826 Feb 26)
William Wirt (1772-1834) asks Archibald Stuart to send his anecdote about Patrick Henry for his biography and to furnish the details just as it was originally told (1816 Aug 10)
MISCELLANEOUS PAPERS OF THE STUART FAMILY (BOXES 1-2)
This series contains an architectural drawing; an engraving of Alexander H.H. Stuart by Danforth, Baldwin & Company; financial and legal papers, including notification of Archibald Stuart 's appointment as a Presidential elector (1792 Nov 12); insurance policies for Archibald Stuart 's barn, grist mill, saw mill, dwelling and kitchen (1811, 1812); Archibald Stuart 's appointment as a commissioner to collect money for a monument to George Washington (1817 Apr 4); stock certificates; accounts and receipts; indentures; land plats; legal cases of both Archibald Stuart and Alexander H.H. Stuart; copies of wills of Alexander Stuart, Robert Stuart, Chapman J. Stuart, and Alexander H.H. Stuart; the military papers of Captain George M. Cochran, Jr., Quartermaster, 52nd Virginian Infantry, Pegram's Brigade, Early's Division; the settlement of Archibald Stuart 's estate, and drafts of several speeches by Alexander H.H. Stuart, one protesting the increase in salary of the superintendent of the Western Asylum because it would be disproportionate to all other salaries allowed by the state of Virginia, another declining the office of President of the branch of the Bank of the Valley and resigning his post as a member of the board, and a third delivered at the fiftieth alumni reunion at the University of Virginia.
CORRESPONDENCE OF ALEXANDER H.H. STUART -SUMMARIES (BOXES 2-4)
Abolitionist (Unidentified) writes a vitriolic letter denouncing slavery and slaveholders and promising his willing participation in the coming revolution to bring about complete democracy (1841 Jun 20)
William H. Allen writes to Alexander H. H. Stuart while he was member of the House of Representatives (1841-1843) seeking his help in establishing a post office at Green Valley, Virginia; the closest one is at Cloverdale (n.y. May 13)
Appomattox County, Virginia, Rough & Ready Club requests Alexander H. H. Stuart to represent the Whig position on the upcoming Presidential election at their next political discussion (1848 Sep 7)
Henry Carey Baird requests a copy of Alexander H. H. Stuart 's recent address to use in his pamphlet concerning the farmers of the United States (1859 Nov 1)
C[ornelius ?] C. Baldwin discusses his biographical sketch of his brother [Gerard ?] Baldwin which he hopes will appear in The Richmond Whig and asks Alexander H. H. Stuart for any comments or additions; he mentions his son, Briscoe G. Baldwin III, a year old and his oldest son, Charles Cornelius (1867 Jan 14)
John B. Baldwin writes concerning business opportunities in Philadelphia ([1843? Jan 30]); Alexander H. H. Stuart 's appointment as Secretary of the Interior and the care of his former legal clients while he is in Washington, D.C. (1850 Sep 24); his disappointment that Millard Fillmore was defeated for the presidential nomination as the Whig candidate; and as Winfield Scott supports the Whig platform without reserve his only objections to Scott as the Whig candidate lies in his great vanity and his associations (1852 Jun 23); Brigadier General Robert Seldon Garnett (1819-1861), who served under General Taylor in the Mexican War, was proceeding to the region with 2500 men according to Alexander H. H. Stuart 's suggestions; and Baldwin believes that the Convention will hardly be well attended (1861 Jun 8); reports that he is within musket range of the enemy who is building winter quarters and mentions the presence of Early's army coming towards [Richmond ?] (1864 Nov 18); writes about his concern over the asylum releasing Briscoe as "incurable but harmless" (1869 Dec 5); and writes to Alexander H. H. Stuart concerning the sale of the "gum tree lot," payment of taxes and an accident of Mayo Cabell; and believes his father may soon be elected Judge ([ca. 1841-1843] Dec 6)
Joseph G. Baldwin writes his cousin concerning his plan to move to California for the opportunities there (1849 Mar 2); a long jesting letter congratulating Alexander H. H. Stuart on his appointment to be Secretary of the Interior and including family news (1850 Sep 27); and describes San Francisco where he has just opened his law practice (1854 Sep 15)
I.L. Barbour, President of the Orange and Alexandria Rail Road Company, writes that he is unable to comply with his financial request (1866 Dec 11)
A.W. Barton urges Alexander H. H. Stuart to help defeat the [ Virginia Reform ?] Convention, "The tremendous opposition to the mixed basis beyond the Alleghany -the indifference upon the whole subject in the valley counties and some division east of the Blue Ridge will enable us to do it" (1850 Apr 22)
S.S. Baxter recommends William D. Delany as Inspector of the Custom House in Norfolk (1851 Nov 24)
Thomas Hart Benton (1782-1838) writes concerning the Brazeau claimants attempts to get Alexander H. H. Stuart to re-open the case he decided last summer and asks him to leave questions about the decision up to the judiciary ([ca. 1851-1853])
Berford & Company, California Express Office, reports a great dissatisfaction of their customers and fellow California Whigs with the appointment of Mr. Beall as Superintendent of Indian Affairs (1852 Apr 12)
Dr. Edmund Berkeley voices his concern over the increase in smallpox cases and attributes the cause to the lack of a vaccine agent in western and central Virginia and suggests Staunton as a likely location for such an agent and offering himself as a candidate (1837 Jan 20)
James B. Bingham, editor of The Intelligencer, discusses politics in Wheeling, [West] Virginia, and his concern that both the Democrats and Republicans are pulling votes away from the Whig Party (1859 Sep 28)
David Alexander Bokee (1805-1860) discusses national politics and urges Alexander H. H. Stuart and other conservatives not to make any arrangements with the Republicans preliminary to the organization of the House; refers to the New York Times article quoting a correspondent from Ohio who believes "the South is beginning to prepare the way for union with the Republicans as such in 1860"; and asks Alexander H. H. Stuart to support the efforts of conservatives of the North "to induce the Republican Party to abandon `its distinct organization' founded as it is `on foolish abstractions" (1859 Oct 24)
Patrick Brady 's letters, from Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, all discuss various aspects of his suit against Daniel Brady, including his stolen ledger which later appears to have been altered, his demand for the deed to the Bath Iron Works, and questions about ultimate settlement (1857, 1867-1869)
Mary Louisa Brooks writes whimsically about how much she misses Washington, D.C., and how unattractive she finds New York City "this huge temple of Mammon" (n.y. Mar 18)
Alexander S. Brown writes his cousin Alexander H. H. Stuart concerning business and family matters (1857-1858)
Joseph Rodes Buchanan asks Alexander H. H. Stuart to attend the National Democratic Convention to be held on May 7, 1867, in Louisville, Kentucky, discussed in an enclosed editorial from The Louisville Journal which was recently identified with the Democratic Party; the Convention to be composed of the leading men of the Northern Democracy and leading men of the South to secure cooperation between the two groups, "which is now our only hope" (1867 Feb 28)
John C. Bullitt, Patrick Brady 's council in Philadelphia, asks when the first remittance of the Brady v. Brady settlement will arrive (1871 Oct 28)
William M. Burwell draws Alexander H. H. Stuart 's attention to the political aspects of the negotiations over the Isthmus of Tehuantepec as a quicker route to the western states (1852 Jul 23)
J.S. Calvert furnishes a financial summary for Alexander H. H. Stuart (1868 Jan 21)
Samuel D. Campbell asks for help in getting payment for his brother William Campbell who worked to get depositions for Catherine Crider in Wardlaw v. Crider (1830 Nov 30)
Lewis Cass (1782-1866) discusses two appointments with Alexander H. H. Stuart acceptable to the Whig Party (1852 Jul 20)
John H. Cassin asks Alexander H. H. Stuart to visit their county and address them concerning the political questions of the day (1859 Apr 13)
Katherine Chase discusses the circumstances surrounding her divorce from Mr. William Sprague (1883 Mar 18)
H. Chrisman offers to purchase real estate or other goods for Alexander H. H. Stuart on his trips west if he wishes (Dec 7, 1855)
Bolivar Christian sends a copy of the Confederate Acts and discusses the problems of setting up the new Confederate Congress (1862 Jan 18)
C.M. Conrad writes concerning Alexander H. H. Stuart 's order for a cask of table claret wine from New Orleans (1855 Apr 3)
William Wilson Corcoran says he will be happy to have a copy of the proceedings of the Peabody Board and hopes to see him soon (1855 Oct 23)
Thomas Corwin (1794-1865) a letter of introduction for [Calhoun Benham], U.S. Attorney for California (1853 Jul 10)
J.A. Cowardin, Editor of The Daily Dispatch, letter of introduction from L.A. Trigg, and a discussion of the Readjuster controversy, and William Mahone, and says "I do not think Mr. Hunter will suit these times. We want an aggressive man, one who is bold and sagacious too. I think General [James Lawson] Kemper is that man" (1873 Feb 14)
John Jordan Crittenden (1786-1863) writes a letter of introduction for his friend Samuel Casey (1851 Sep 26)
Claudius Crozet writes concerning the Northwest Turnpike and asks if Alexander H. H. Stuart feels that Mr. Eskridge is capable of opening the road himself (1838 Jun 1)
Rector E.A. Dalrymple 's recommendation of Thomas B. Edelin (1852 Jul 15)
John W. Daniel (1842-1910) does not approve of the Readjuster policies, "I am firm against repudatum alias enforced readjustment alias stealing. I believe in the Decalogue, and of course in repressing thieves, by whatsoever name they are called" (1877 Jul 18)
J.D. Davidson sends the election results for Rockbridge County (1851 Dec 10) and encloses a check for a claim against Seaforth (1852 Jan 2)
Garrett Davis (1801-1872) discusses a power shift in the House of Representatives away from [John C.] Calhoun toward [Thomas Hart?] Benton who "will be the dictator this winter & will wield more power than all others together"; mentions the numerous job seekers wandering the halls of Congress like unclean birds; discusses the hopes of the Whig Party to gain the Presidency next election and mentions possible opponents and weighs their respective threat to the chances of the Whig candidate; and the need for much organization and work to succeed in the next election (1843 Dec 13); a long and detailed description of the difficulty during the extra session of the 27th Congress in organizing the House caused by the opposition of the Democrats and the division in the Whig Party (1845 Dec 16); the third letter discusses business questions; congratulates Alexander H. H. Stuart on his appointment to be Secretary of the Interior; expresses his appreciation for Millard Fillmore; and comments about South Carolina, " South Carolina is a little beside herself, but I believe it is the insanity of ambition pride & arrogance thwarted, and that a good sound drubbing would be an infallible cure." (1851 Jan 28)
George M. Davis thanks Alexander H. H. Stuart for giving his son Carey Davis a job as a clerk in the Pension Office (1851 Jul 27)
William Wallace Davis, editor of The District Whig discusses politics in Norfolk and the loss of the election to the Democrats despite his own efforts to visit various Whigs and get them to the polls on Election Day (1851 Oct 2)
William Crosby Dawson (1798-1856), Georgia Senator, asks Alexander H. H. Stuart not to fill a vacancy in the General Land Office until he could speak with him (1852 Jul 28)